Kassoy, Bernard Teachers Union Cartoons 6107 G
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Baseball scoreboard announces major successes for Teacher Union, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  April 30, 1960. "Budget Brief at City Hall," "Educational Conference at Waldorf-Astoria," "Victory in Ayman-Greenwood Suit Wins 60 Million for Teachers." Coincident with the opening of the baseball season, the school spring season opens with three important Teachers Union achievements: The budget brief presented to City Hall, the highly successful Annual Educational Conference at the Waldorf-Astoria Hotel, and its outstanding victory in winning $60 million in pension increases for teachers in the successful Ayman-Greenwood suit.
- Representative of the Board of Education sits outside a door with students bulging out of the classroom door. He shows a Sorry no job next term sign to a woman with a 243 Fall Term Subs folder, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  January 13, 1962.
- Man next to marquee reading BD. of ED. meets today. Agenda: Afternoon: hearing on teachers salary. Evening: Adopt salary schedule (Quick work!) (Box 2, Folder 84)
- Two birds on a branch over a nest. Birds are labeled more city funds and more state aid funds., 1962 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  January 20, 1962. Two eggs in a nest below them are labeled "Schinnerer Report" and "Superintendents and Examiners recommendations".
- Dont Let it Happen, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  March 26, 1960. Two men stand next to a large covered platter marked "salary raise". One says "This much for me" with arms spread wide. The other says the same, spreading his arms wide. The first lifts the cover to reveal a tiny amount to be divided. (In three frames) Teachers are urged not to fight among themselves for the greater share of the pittance of a wage increase offered them.
- Young woman in shadow is labeled 99% overcrowded classes, under paid teachers, overburdened [sic] staffs, dilapidated buildings, shortage of teachers, witch hunts, etc etc, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  February 15, 1958. A tiny man representing the Board of Education shines a light on "1% delinquents"
- [illegible text around border] To All- A Well-Earned Holiday, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  December 18, 1954. Young man dressed as Santa Claus labeled "all of us" carrying a bag labeled "good deeds in '54: TU drive for staff unity on compromise pay plan; Legislators praise TU budget briefs; TU primer for new teachers in wide demand; 1600 at Russell testimonial dinner Build the TU; Puerto Rico supplement and Jewish tercentenary issues open school week leaflet reach scores of thousands of [no more]; TU defends academic fre; $'s in pension gains"
- An Unequal Match, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  January 27, 1951. Chess pieces on board which represents "The Spartan Queen" with its "Rent Rises" sign. The knight is labeled "tax Increases" and the pawn in scholar's garb is labeled "Teachers' $250 pittance". [number 378 at bottom front, and verso has 889/IHIL]]
- Child reads a despairing man a List of supplies for school that goes on and on. Blue at bottom text lists items and prices and did you say free public schools? (Box 2, Folder 90)
- Watch Out! Booby Traps!, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  October 20, 1951. A teacher stands scratching his head next to a rifle and army helmet labeled "extra-curricular stoppage", looking over a barbed wire fenced middle ground towards a goal over the far hills of "$4000-$8000 Salary". Between them is "elementary school vs. high school"; "coercion"; "red-baiting mine field"; fear"; "disunity;" and "misleaders". [labeled 5 200/2-2] Teachers are cautioned not to be misled by the phony promises of salary increases so that they ignore the genuine threats posed by so-called leaders who sow disunity between elementary and high school teachers and who give their silent assent to the persecution of teachers for their political benefits.
- Young man carries a sign reading the high school teacher program card for 1959-1960" (Box 2, Folder 92)
  November 21, 1959. Listing English classes and registrations from 38-42 students and "more papers to mark, heavier clerical load, building assignments, etc, etc., Another sign reads Notice: The Board of Education reports that the average high school class register has dropped by 0.1 pupil! From 31.8 to 31.7. [ in bottom border is number 120]
- Woman holds sheets of paper., 1900 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  One held by a bird above her reads "for the new year UNITE! Teachers Union Teachers Guild H.S.T.A others all" Her sheets read, "Increased work load for teachers, Inadequate buildings, worse overcrowding, low salary".
- Young girl holding a battered science text dated circa 1940 says to her father [in blue pencil in page border] but Dad, how can I do my science homework- I cant find any pages on outer space in this book., 1962 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  February 03, 1962.
- Cauldron with steam rising, on hook over fire. No text. (Box 2, Folder 95)
- In a classroom, Saul stands by a desk that supports a tape recorder. (Box 2, Folder 96)
  A man in black coat, hat, and dark glasses sits, in a waste basket [?], saying "names, names, names, names. Saul signs a check [?] for "$25 per day".
- An Inspiring Teacher, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 97)
  February 02, 1952. Two boys, one black and one white, comfortably share a desk and a book, reading together. Above them is a profile of Franklin D. Roosevelt.
- Forbidden Territory, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 98)
  February 14, 1953. The "Thought Police" blows his whistle to stop school bus at an "out of bounds" intersection. Directional signs read "education, controversy, independent thought, and criticism". [Penciled in is "forbidden territory"]
- Lest We forget, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 99)
  November 21, 1953. "Mr. New Mayor" sits in front of the calendar for 1954. A man representing labor hold the list of "campaign pledges" including "pay raise for teachers, more school buildings, reduce overcrowding, a new deal for all, little Wagner Act for civil". [On back 170/13-3] The teacher is here reminding newly elected New York City Mayor Robert F. Wagner of his campaign pledges of a pay raise for teachers, more school buildings, reducing overcrowding, a New Deal for all, and Little Wagner Act for civil service employees- a reference to the act bearing the name of the mayor's father, Senator Robert Wagner, that gave workers the right to organize and bargain collectively.
- Excess Story, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 100)
  June 14, 1952. A man sits at a desk writing an "excess list" and admonishing a teacher carrying "certificates of competence" in drafting, English, and other studies.
- A black woman and black girl sit together at a table with a copy of The First Reader. (Box 2, Folder 101)
- No Others Need Apply, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 102)
  May 17, 1952. Board of Education prospective candidates represented by placards for "banker, trust company attorney, corporate executive, big business man, real estate, manufacturer, utilities man, textile executive, and Tammany hack". ["No others need apply- the Mayor" penciled in the border]. Mayor Vincent Impelliterri was strongly criticized by the Teacher's Union for confining his appointments to the Board of Education to such persons as bankers, trust company attorneys, etc..
- The Board of Education, with assistance from big money, wields the 903 sledge hammer knocking down the wall of tenure laws, outstanding records, long years of service and scholarship., 1952 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  October 11, 1952. (One of the victims of the school witch-hunt, Irving Adler, has achieved international renown as a leading mathematician. Columbia University could hardly wait for the Board of Education to let him go so that they could hire him. Similarly, the United States Military Academy at West Point has been eager to use his services to teach the cadets at that institution.) [On back is 7480/6-5]
- A little girl talks to Santa Claus asking and please bring Daddy a raise so he can stay home and play with me instead of going to work as a Santa Claus in Gimbals, and [On back is 1705/12-2] (Box 2, Folder 104)
- Big business with arms orders and money in his pocket, in addition to 111% rise in real personal income, sits on inflation which is carried on the back of workers. (Box 2, Folder 105)
- At Least Its a Step Forward, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 106)
  April 05, 1952. The "staff relations plan", a noose around the neck of the worker, pulls him off the edge of a cliff onto sharpened spikes of "recognized " only, no "policy" matters, no salary matters, no pensions discussed, the superintendent decides, the Board rules, we'll arbitrate if the Board feels like it". [Penciled at the bottom "At lease it's a step forward"] [On the back is 6389/4-4]
- A Program for All Teachers, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 107)
  May 03, 1952. The very large hand of Samuel Greenfield, Board member of the Teacher's Union, points to a teachers retirement system document that reads "retirement with security and dignity, program of refo[rm]" [In the border "For all teachers"]. He was a recognized expert on matters of pensions and finances. At a time when the Teacher's Retirement System was mired in mismanagement, Greenfield proposed reforms that would guarantee teachers "retirement with security and dignity."
- A jack-in-the-box overcrowding bursts the roof off a public school building that is coming apart at the walls with the too many students coming out of windows and doors., 1952 (Box 2, Folder 108)
  October 04, 1952.
- Help for the mountain climber, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 109)
  December 12, 1953. The hand of "salary raise" is held out to a worker struggling to climb above "food, medical services, rent, clothing, taxes, and the cost of living".
- The Only Language They Understand, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 110)
  March 07, 1953. Very large worker holds a sign that reads "United Teachers salary campaign. All organizations back one bill" over the capitol and a legislator in Albany. Legislators in Albany will only be impressed and moved to action by a United Teachers Salary Campaign in which all teacher organizations back the same piece of legislation.
- Supervisor Into Inquisitor, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 111)
  March 15, 1952. Large box leaning over a desk toward an employee (just off frame). A paper in the waste basket reads "Civil Service Law". No one may be questioned concerning his political beliefs or affiliations or opinions" The "creepy" figure (literally) used by Bernard Kassoy to represent the school inquisitor is shown here throwing the Civil Service Law guarantees of freedom of beliefs and association into the waste basket.
- The Most Unkindest Cut of All, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 112)
  January 19, 1952. "The sub", the "most vulnerable member of the teaching staff of all," is holding on to the end of a rope over "unemployment" and is about to be cut off and allowed to fall on "Feb. 1" by large scissors. (See "The Lament of the Substitute" at the end of this year's selection of cartoons).
- Operation Meat Grinder, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 113)
  January 30, 1954. A pay check goes through the grinder of "1954 costs" and comes out in tiny bits of "purchasing power". [on the bottom border is penciled 3567/4-4]
- Were Aiming Only at Reds, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 114)
  June 07, 1952. In the "red" hunt, the "American Legion and Catholic War Vets attack the NEA" gun shoots a soldier towards "academic freedom, NEA, Dean Lenz, the public schools, Mrs. Bethune and progressive education"
- Both Democrats and Republicans turn their backs on the baby labeled taxes to pay for school services. [on the front is 381, on the back is 4737/1] (Box 2, Folder 115)
- Girl holds a sign reading Another homework assignment for YOU! For more and better new schools vote YES on amendment #4 [on the border is 129], 1959 (Box 2, Folder 116)
  October 24, 1959.
- Solution, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 117)
  June 04, 1955. Man at a podium labeled "official voices, editorials, politicians" says "we must arrange to solve these pressing problems." With a sign reading "retardation increased delinquency tension language groups". Crowded freshman classroom, September 1955, with students standing has "the arrangement: high school class registers to increase in 1955-56 school year"
- A man with a Salary Plan walks to the office of the Mayor through [illegible ision] Groups, T.I.C. Groups, School Groups, K-6B Groups, High School Groups, Boro-Wide Groups, Subject-Matter Groups, Vocational Groups (Box 2, Folder 118)
  [penciled on the back "used"]
- In Need of a Helping Hand, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 119)
  March 11, 1961. The large hand of "Federal Aid 1961" reaches down to a child with arms raised.
- One Roadblock Removed, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 120)
  October 28, 1961. At the turn of a path marked "to CB" a man pushes a bolder labeled "Interference with freedom to campaign"
- In three frames. A finger beckons a turkey. The turkey has a dog tag tossed around its neck. The hand wielding a hatchet swings at the turkey which dodges. (Box 2, Folder 121)
- [Border reads in the good old budget time] (Box 2, Folder 122)
  On a theatrical stage the Act is indicated as "Ye same olde budget time Act", a banner "Pay raise for teachers" tops the stage, and three dancing men "BD of ED., The City, and the State" all point at each other.
- Under a large question mark is The future for education. (Box 2, Folder 123)
  Below it 2 men claim credit for success "What a wonderful job we've done for education" "No, no, it was really us, we did it, we are" [on the border it says "Almost lost in the storm"]
- On the table is a note Pay raise for subs delayed to September A masked man points a gun at the sub with a note $75 less on your check (Box 2, Folder 124)
- Demands for a united salary fight over stacks of letters, Letters; clerks; T.I.C.s; unaffiliated teachers; young teachers; resolutions; subs; faculties; UNITE!; outworn separate-isms (Box 2, Folder 125)
- Ask City Hall to Defrost the Teachers Salary Bill, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 126)
  March 11, 1950. The City Council's ways and means committee skates on an ice block containing the "Roman salary bill" over the Albany capitol building while the need for these increases grows. [3399/1 on back]
- Male and female students outside a high school classroom. [Border reads just think, I only stand up in 3 classes out of five (Box 2, Folder 127)
- The president standing on his head. A hand points to a sign, more money now! [Penciled on the border is Levitt: - make a study of the situation (Box 2, Folder 128)
- We Do need that Raise, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 129)
  September 16, 1950. In August worker leaves the summer job bent over and exhausted. In September, school opens and the worker is again bent over having to deal with low pay, overcrowding, and intimidation. [In two frames]
- September, absence deduction made-pronto! when worker is home with a fever. In October no refund yet. But the bills come in. November has no refund yet but the bills mound up. December Swamped with bills. (Box 2, Folder 130)
  In four frames. [penciled on back 2358/1-2]
- Evening high school CLOSED. A united staff demands pay raise now! BD of ED escorts a scab to work., 1959 (Box 2, Folder 131)
  February 14, 1959.
- Hand writing a note (Box 2, Folder 132)
  "having expressed my appreciation for the wonderful job TU has been doing for years in the fight for better education, I think it's time I stopped just applauding from the sidelines and JOINED THE TEACHERS UNION.. Fraternally, Young Teacher"
- Waiter serves a platter with Board of Estimate Order: One small 'slice-it-yourself' pie for 40,000 teachers. (Box 2, Folder 133)
  Four teacher "spokesmen" show how to slice it saying "this way!" "No! This way!" "It's mine!" "Like this!"
- Too much to ask?, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 134)
  October 22, 1955. A representative of the City Planning Commission has plans for the sewer, traffic, pavement, parks, buses, subways, hospitals, housing" and a child taps him on the arm with a thought of "a seat for every child". [An embossed seal on lower left corner shows a Scottish thistle and says "Strathmore Use either side"]
- Father time with sickle and New Year infant carrying banner Seasons Greetings to All. (Box 2, Folder 135)
- A Happy Summer to All From the Teachers Union to the School Staffs. Staff and students carry suitcases labeled with European city names [small coffee stain at bottom of page] (Box 2, Folder 136)
- A very large Abraham Lincoln in the shadows behind a white and black student walking together [Must for tonight]. Digital only. Original returned to Mr. Kassoy. (Box 2, Folder 137)
- Brittle - Mexican Labor Posters (Box 3)